<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Jez Cope (Scholarly Communication)</title><link>http://jcope.shef.ac.uk/</link><description></description><atom:link type="application/rss+xml" rel="self" href="http://jcope.shef.ac.uk/categories/scholarly-communication.xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 20 Sep 2016 10:46:22 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>https://getnikola.com/</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Overleaf Conference, July 2016</title><link>http://jcope.shef.ac.uk/notes/overleaf/</link><dc:creator>Jez Cope</dc:creator><description>&lt;!--
.. title: Overleaf Conference, July 2016
.. slug: overleaf
.. date: 2016-07-27 15:15:54 UTC+01:00
.. tags: Overleaf,Scholarly Communication,Collaboration,Publishing
.. category: Meetings
.. link: 
.. description: 
.. type: text
--&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Tuesday 12 July 2016 I went to London to learn more about a product called &lt;a href="https://overleaf.com"&gt;Overleaf&lt;/a&gt;. Being arranged at the last minute at quite a busy time of year for many people, it was quite a select gathering, which lent itself well to some interesting conversations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overleaf is a collaborative online writing tool that could be described as the offspring of a beautiful union between &lt;a href="https://docs.google.com/"&gt;Google Docs&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://latex-project.org/"&gt;LaTeX&lt;/a&gt;. It gives the same live simultaneous editing experience of Docs, but produces beautifully typeset PDF documents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In practice, that means that authors working on a report or paper can collaborate easily without getting lost in a flurry of emails and Microsoft Word tracked changes. Instead there's a single online version of the document that all authors can edit simultaneously. If you've ever tried it with Google Docs you'll know that editing a document at the same time as several other people can be slightly unnerving, but very effective once you get used to it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unlike Google Docs though, Overleaf is based on a typesetting engine called LaTeX which turns simple text into fully typeset documents. It has excellent support for mathematical notation and reference management, so it's been well used for decades in areas like mathematics, physics and computer science and is increasingly computational scientists and engineers in areas such as biology and chemistry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The really interesting part is Overleaf's integration with publishers' platforms. You can submit your manuscript directly to one of their publisher partners with just a button click, and the list of partners is constantly growing. A lot of journals have LaTeX templates that give an approximation of how your manuscript will appear when published, and it's now possible to start a new manuscript for these journals in Overleaf with a single click too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For us in Research Services in the library, that means there's a well-defined author's accepted manuscript that can potentially be deposited into our institutional repository with just a few button clicks, with all the metadata already available. That could make both our lives and our researchers' much easier. The Overleaf developers seemed really interested in this possibility, so we could see a "deposit accepted manuscript" button appearing soon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That's the theory, anyway: I haven't yet used it enough to get an appreciation of whether or not it works in practice, but it sounds like a great idea and I'll be keeping an eye on it as it develops.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>Collaboration</category><category>Overleaf</category><category>Publishing</category><category>Scholarly Communication</category><guid>http://jcope.shef.ac.uk/notes/overleaf/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 27 Jul 2016 14:15:54 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>